Guide to the Henry Stuart Hughes Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Henry Stuart Hughes papers
1916-2000
MS 1446
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10.75
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, campaign records, personal papers, and photographs documenting the life and career of Henry Stuart Hughes. The collection documents Hughes' military career during and after World War II, his 1962 senatorial campaign, his tenure as co-chair and chair of the National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy (SANE), his academic career and writings, and his personal life.
Hughes, H. Stuart (Henry Stuart), 1916-1999
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of H. Stuart Hughes, 1986, 1989. Gift of Judith M. Hughes, 1999, 2000, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Stuart Hughes was born May 7, 1916 in New York City, the son of Charles Evans Hughes, Jr. and Marjory Stuart Hughes. His grandfather was Charles Evans Hughes, former Secretary of State and Chief Justice of the Supreme Court. H. Stuart Hughes attended Amherst College (B.A. 1937) and Harvard University (Ph.D., History 1940). Before enlisting in the armed services, Hughes taught briefly at Brown University in 1940 1941.
In 1941, Hughes enlisted as a private in the Rhode Island National Guard. Later that year, he joined the Office of the Coordinator of Information within the Office of Strategic Services in Washington D.C. Hughes served in a variety of administrative and research capacities in the O.S.S. during the war, in a number of different venues, including Algeria, France, Italy, England and Germany. He was promoted several times, and was eventually elevated to the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. With the end of the war in 1945, Hughes returned to Washington and took a position in the Department of State.
In 1947, Hughes left the Department of State and returned to Harvard to teach half time in the Department of History and to be associate director of the Russian Research Center. Hughes was denied tenure at Harvard in 1952. He taught at Stanford University from 1952 to 1956 when he returned to the Harvard history department as an Associate Professor. Hughes remained at Harvard until 1975, when both he and his second wife, Judith, accepted positions in the history department at the University of California at San Diego. Throughout his distinguished academic career, Hughes published many books and articles on European history, and was acknowledged as one of the foremost voices in the field of European intellectual history.
In 1962, Hughes ran for the United States Senate as an independent candidate from the state of Massachusetts. Although Hughes finished third in a race won by Edward Kennedy, his candidacy was one of the first to emphasize peace and nuclear disarmament at the center of a campaign platform. In 1963, he became co chairman, with Benjamin Spock, of the board of directors of the National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy, known more commonly as SANE. Hughes stayed on as chairman of SANE, after Spock stepped down from the position in 1967, until 1970. He also was an active and outspoken critic of the Vietnam war who published articles, gave speeches and attended protests in opposition to the conflict.
Hughes' leftist leanings resulted in his being suspected as a subversive on at least two occasions. In the early 1950s, he was forced to resign his military commission due to allegations that he was a communist sympathizer, although he was given an honorable discharge. In 1966, he was temporarily refused a visa to travel abroad by the State Department on charges he was a communist conspirator, which were later dropped.
Hughes married twice and had three children, Sandra and Kenneth with his first wife Suzanne, and David, with his second wife Judith. He retired from the University of California at San Diego in 1986. In 1990, he published his autobiography, Gentleman Rebel: The Memoirs of H. Stuart Hughes. Henry Stuart Hughes died October 21, 1999.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, campaign records, personal papers, and photographs documenting the life and career of Henry Stuart Hughes. The collection documents Hughes' military career during and after World War II, his 1962 senatorial campaign, his tenure as co-chair and chair of the National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy (SANE), his academic career and writings, and his personal life.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and two additions: I. Correspondence, 1945-1989. II. Senate Campaign Records, 1962-1964. III. Writings and Teaching Matrials, 1948-1990. IV. Personal Papers and Photographs, 1916-1989.
Audio Tape Appendix
1 "Approaches to European Intellectual History" [Symposium honoring HSH], tape 1 90 minute cassette, TDK D90
2 "Approaches to European Intellectual History" [Symposium honoring HSH], tape 2 90 minute cassette, TDK D90
3 "Approaches to European Intellectual History" [Symposium honoring HSH], tape 3 90 minute cassette, TDK D90
4 "Approaches to European Intellectual History" [Symposium honoring HSH], tape 4 90 minute cassette, TDK D90
5 "Approaches to European Intellectual History" [Symposium honoring HSH], tape 5 90 minute cassette, TDK D90
Massachusetts -- Politics and government; Historians; Hughes, H. Stuart (Henry Stuart), 1916-1999; Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy
- Correspondence, 1945 1989; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged alphabetically by individual and corporate names and broad subject area, Correspondence primarily documents the professional activities of H. Stuart Hughes. The correspondence ranges from 1945 to 1989, but the bulk of the material falls between 1958 and the late 1970s. Hughes' own organizational structure for the files has been largely retained, and relevant cross references have been created.
  Arranged chronologically, materials listed under "National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy" (SANE) document Hughes' participation in the group, most notably from 1963 to 1970 when he served first as a co chair with Benjamin Spock and subsequently as chairman of the board of directors. Correspondence with SANE staff members Sanford Gottlieb, Donald Keyes, and Marie Runyon, as well as other board members such as Spock, Norman Cousins, Norman Thomas, Nathan Glazer, and Homer Jack make up the bulk of the section. Memoranda circulated among the board members and the staff, but not written by or specifically to Hughes, are also included. The files give a good representation of the activities of the group and particularly document the internal conflicts of the organization. Related but separate groups of materials pertaining to Hughes' anti war work are grouped under the headings "Vietnamese Conflict" and "Massachusetts Political Action for Peace (PAX)."
  The series also contains much correspondence relating to Hughes' intellectual endeavors. Letters to and from many prominent intellectuals of his time, including Vladimir Dedijer, Erik Erikson, John K. Fairbank, Richard Hofstadter, James Joll, Herbert Marcuse, and David Riesman among others, provide insight into Hughes' scholarship. Hughes' correspondence with his several publishers, including Atheneum, Harper and Row, Harvard University Press, Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., Prentice Hall, and University of Chicago Press documents the publication process of his many books. For additional correspondence relating to Hughes' intellectual work, researchers should consult the Books section of the Writings series.
  Hughes' writings on politics and other contemporary issues, including United States foreign policy, nuclear deterrence and the Vietnam War, are further documented in his correspondence with the editors of magazines for which he wrote. Files on Martin Greenberg (Commentary) and Robert Silvers (Harper's Magazine and New York Review of Books) are particularly revealing.
  Hughes' active participation in many professional societies and other organizations is documented in the series. Groups of note include American Committee on Soviet Jewry, American Committee for the History of the Second World War, Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions, and the Congressional Liberal Group. The series also covers Hughes' tenure in his two most significant academic appointments: Harvard University and the University of California at San Diego.
  The series holds additional correspondence of a more personal nature, to and from friends such as Lise de Carbonnel, Fairman Cowan, Robert L. Edwards, Albert Guérard, Sr., Hans Meyerhoff, Allan Mitchell, Franco Venturi, and Roberto Vivarelli. Correspondence with family members, particularly Hughes' parents, can be found in Series IV.
  - A (General), 1959-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Academic Committee on Soviet Jewry, 1972-1973, 1978-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1968, 1975-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Committee for the History of the Second World War, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 5)
  - American Historical Association, 1968-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Professors for Peace in the Middle East, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Psychiatric Association, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Scholar, 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Anshen, Ruth [re: conflict with Department of State], 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Atheneum Publishers, 1959-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - B (General), 1958-1987 (Box 1, Folder 13 - 14)
  - Berlin, Isaiah, 1961, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bolaffio, Robert E., 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Boyers, Robert
    General note
    See: Series I, folder 163
  - Breines, Paul, 1970, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Brinton, Crane, 1959, 1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    See also: Series III, folder 40
  - Bundy, McGeorge, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Burdett, Winston, 1958-1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - C (General), 1958-1985 (Box 1, Folder 21 - 23)
  - Canfield, Cass
    See: Series I, folder 64-65
  - de Carbonnel, Lise, 1944-1989 (Box 2, Folder 24 - 29)
  - Casalini, Mario, 1958-1976 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    See also: Series I, folder 46
  - Chevreaux, Lise
    See: Series I, folder 24-29
  - Clifford, James, 1971-1983 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Commentary
    See: Series I, folder 55; Series I, folder 142
  - Conference on the Stature of Soviet Jews
    See: Series I, folder 36
  - Congressional Liberal Group
    See: Series I, folder 92
  - Conn, Stetson
    See: Series I, folder 4-5
  - Cousins, Norman
    See: Series I, folder 123 - 131
  - Cowan, Fairman, 1961-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 33 & 34)
    See also: Series IV, folder 65
  - D (General), 1957-1983 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Decter, Moshe, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Dedijer, Vladimir, 1962-1974, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Dickinson, Edwin, 1958, 1964-1972, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Ditlev-Simonsen, Per, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Donald, Aida
    See: Series I, folder 75
  - Dunlop, John, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - E (General), 1957-1988 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Edwards, Robert L., 1964-1989 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Erikson, Erik H., undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - F (General), 1958-1981 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Fairbank, John King, 1967-1973 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Ferry, W. H. ["Ping"], 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    See also: Series I, folder 31
  - Fleming, Donald, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Ford Hall Forum, 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Fromm, Erich, 1959-1968 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Funk, Arthur
  - G (General), 1958-1985 (Box 3, Folder 50 - 51)
  - Gay, Peter, 1958, 1964-1965, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Geertz, Clifford, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Gilbert, Felix, 1960-1985 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Glazer, Nathan
    See: Series I, folder 123-131
  - Gottleib, Sanford
  - Greenberg, Martin, 1957-1968 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Grossman, Jerome, 1964-1977, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Guérard, Albert Sr., 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Guérard, Albert Jr. and Maclin, 1959-1968 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - H (General), 1958-1986 (Box 3, Folder 59 - 62)
  - Hanslowe, Kurt L., 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Harper and Row Publishers, 1965-1980 (Box 3, Folder 64 - 65)
  - Harper's Magazine
    See: Series I, folder 171
  - Harvard University
    - General, 1965-1975 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - African American Studies Program, 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Center for International Affairs, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Department of History
      - General, 1963-1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
      - Job offer, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 70)
      - Overseer's Committee to Visit the Department of History, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Faculty Council, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Kendall Foundation, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Undergraduate curriculum, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Harvard University Press, 1973, 1979-1985 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Hayden, Hiram
    See: Series I, folder 10; Series I, folder 12
  - Higgonet, Patrick, 1958-1973 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Hoffman, Stanley, 1961-1966 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Hofstadter Richard and Bede, 1963-1972 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Howard, Marghanita, 1960-1964 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Howe, Irving, 1961-1970 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - I (General), 1960-1981 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - International Committee on the History of the Second World War
  - International Council of the Future of the University, 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Izenberg, Gerald, 1965-1966, 1975-1977, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - J (General), 1959-1982 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Jack, Homer
  - Jay, Martin, 1968-1983 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Jemolo, Arturo Carlo, 1963, 1967-1981 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Joll, James, 1965-1968, 1979-1988 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - K (General), 1958-1986 (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Kapstein, Ethan, 1970-1981 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Kapstein, John J., 1961-1986 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Kapstein, Matthew, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Katzenmaier, Robert, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Kent, Sherman, 1968-1976 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Keys, Donald
  - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1957-1961, 1973-1977, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Kreiger, Leonard, 1960-1976 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - L (General), 1958-1989 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Landes, David, 1964-1974 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Lawler, Justus George, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Léger, Bernard, 1947, 1958-1977 (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Lichtheim, George, 1959-1965 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Lifton, Robert J., 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - Loewenstein, Karl, 1965-1971 (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Luft, David, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - M (General), 1958-1985 (Box 4, Folder 104 - 106)
  - Maier, Charles S., 1966, 1971, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - Mannucci, Cesare and Loretta, 1961-1983 (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - Marcuse, Herbert and Inge, 1959-1979 (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - Massachusetts Political Action for Peace
    See: Series I, folder 139
  - McCarthy, Eugene, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Meisner, Maurice, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Meyerhoff, Hans, 1947-1965 (Box 5, Folder 112 - 113)
  - Michel, Henri, 1961-1966 (Box 5, Folder 114)
    See also: Series I, folder 4-5
  - Mills, C. Wright, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Mitchell, Allan, 1957-1980 (Box 5, Folder 116)
    See also: Series I, folder 183
  - Momigliano, Arnaldo D., 1968-1971, 1981-1983 (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Moore, Barrington, 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Moynihan, Daniel Patrick, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - Mumford, Lewis, 1952, 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 120)
  - Muste, A. J., 1965-1966, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 121)
  - N (General), 1959-1983 (Box 5, Folder 122)
  - National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy
    - General, 1960-1973, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 123 - 131)
    - Publicity [flyers, press releases, statements, newsletters], 1968-1972 (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - Regional organizations, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 133)
  - Neuhaus, Richard John
  - New York Review of Books
  - O (General), 1957-1984 (Box 5, Folder 134)
  - P (General), 1958-1982 (Box 6, Folder 135 - 136)
  - Packard, Lenore
  - Padberg, John, 1962-1965, 1975, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 137)
  - Partisan Review, 1960-1966 (Box 6, Folder 138)
  - PAX [Massachusetts Political Action for Peace], 1963-1970, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 139)
  - Paxton, Robert, 1972-1973, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 140)
  - Peretz, Martin, 1964-1971, 1977, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 141)
    See also: Series I, folder 123-131
  - Podhoretz, Norman, 1960-1976 (Box 6, Folder 142)
  - Polin, Raymond, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 143)
  - Prentice-Hall, Inc., 1957-1985 (Box 6, Folder 144 - 149)
  - Psychohistory, 1966-1971 (Box 6, Folder 150)
  - R (General), 1957-1983 (Box 6, Folder 151 - 152)
  - Ratté, John, 1963-1968 (Box 6, Folder 153)
  - Rhome, John O., 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 154)
  - Riasnovsky, Alexander, 1958-1967, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 155)
  - Ricci, Rinaldo, 1945-1947, 1963, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 156)
  - Riesman, David, 1959-1975 (Box 6, Folder 157)
  - Robinson, Paul, 1966-1968, 1977, 1986, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 158)
  - Runyon, Marie
  - S (General), 1957-1986 (Box 7, Folder 159 - 162)
  - Salamagundi, 1968-1974 (Box 7, Folder 163)
  - Salomone, A. William, 1969-1975 (Box 7, Folder 164)
  - SANE
  - Schenker, Steve, 1965, 1975-1978 (Box 7, Folder 165)
  - Schorske, Carl E., 1959-1968, 1975, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 166)
  - Segre-Amar, Sion, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 167)
  - Senn, Edouard, 1958-1971 (Box 7, Folder 168)
  - Shafer, Boyd, 1957-1960 (Box 7, Folder 169)
  - Silone, Ignazio, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 170)
  - Silvers, Robert B., 1960-1978 (Box 7, Folder 171)
  - Simons, Thomas, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 172)
  - Smith, Denis Mack, 1957-1969, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 173)
  - Spini, Giorgio, 1960-1967 (Box 7, Folder 174)
  - Spock, Benjamin, 1964, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 175)
  - Stern, Fritz, 1967-1979 (Box 7, Folder 176)
  - Students for a Democratic Society
    - General, 1963-1965 (Box 7, Folder 177)
    - Radical Education Project, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 178)
  - T (General), 1957-1968 (Box 7, Folder 179)
  - Thomas, Edgar
    See: Series I, folder 144-149
  - Thomas, Norman, 1959-1968 (Box 7, Folder 180)
  - Tillona, Francesca
  - Toews, John, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 181)
  - U (General), 1957-1967 (Box 7, Folder 182)
  - United States Army
    See: Series IV, folder 65
  - University of California San Diego
    - General, 1974-1986, undated (Box 7, Folder 183)
      See also: Series I, folder 116
    - "Approaches to European Intellectual History" [symposium in honor of HSH], 1986 (Box 7, Folder 184)
  - University of Chicago Press, 1966-1982 (Box 7, Folder 185)
  - University of Pennsylvania, 1965, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 186)
  - University of Virginia [re: Richards Lectures], 1970 (Box 7, Folder 187)
  - V (General), 1957-1967 (Box 8, Folder 188)
  - Valiani, Leo, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 189)
  - Venturi, Franco, 1961-1987 (Box 8, Folder 190)
  - Giambattista Vico Tricentennial Symposium, 1966-1968, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 191)
  - Vietnamese Conflict, 1965-1973 (Box 8, Folder 192 - 194)
  - Vivarelli, Roberto, 1965-1985 (Box 8, Folder 195)
  - W (General), 1957-1984 (Box 8, Folder 196 - 197)
  - Waskow, Arthur I., 1962-1970 (Box 8, Folder 198)
  - Wehler, Hans Ulrich, 1971-1974 (Box 8, Folder 199)
  - Wilkinson, James and Jennifer, 1975-1985 (Box 8, Folder 200)
  - Woodward, C. Vann, 1961, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 201)
  - Y-Z (General), 1958-1987 (Box 8, Folder 202)
- Senate Campaign Files, 1962 1964; Series II
  The series documents Hughes' 1962 campaign for a Massachusetts seat in United States Senate as an independent candidate who stressed arms control and peace issues. Correspondence arranged alphabetically within five consecutive chronological periods comprises the bulk of the series. Mail from supporters and detractors of the campaign and inter campaign correspondence and memoranda are included. A history of the campaign written in 1964 provides an excellent overview. Newsletters, statements, press releases, speech texts, and administrative records complete the series.
  - Clippings, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1962
      - Mar-Jun (A-Z) (Box 9, Folder 2-6)
      - Jul-Sep (A-Z) (Box 9, Folder 7 - 12)
      - Sep-Oct (A-Z) (Box 10, Folder 13-17)
      - Oct (A-Z) (Box 10, Folder 18-22)
      - Nov-Dec (A-Z) (Box 11, Folder 23-27)
  - "Hughes for Senate: A Campaign History" [by Joel Cohen; forward by HSH], 1964 (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Newsletters, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - Platform statement, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Press Releases, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Publicity [flyers and mailings], 1962 (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Signature drive, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 33)
  - Speeches, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 34-35)
  - Staff meeting minutes, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 36)
- Writings and Teaching Materials, 1948-1990; Series III
  The series is arranged in six sections: articles and essays; books; book reviews; lectures, remarks and memoranda; student writings; and teaching materials. Each section is organized chronologically.
  Typescripts of short works published in books and academic and mainstream journals comprise articles and essays. Topics vary widely but include Italian and French history, historiography, American foreign policy, the Vietnam war, and nuclear disarmament. One folder of autobiographical essays is located at the beginning of the section.
  Books include correspondence, notes, drafts, outlines, and reviews of Hughes' many monographs. Correspondence relating to a publication includes comments from other academics and intellectuals. Researchers should also consult the files in Series I for Hughes' various publishers (Atheneum, Harper and Row, Harvard University Press, Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., Prentice Hall, and University of Chicago Press) for further documentation on the publication of his books.
  The remainder of the series is comprised of four smaller sections. Book reviews contains reviews Hughes wrote for academic and mainstream intellectual serials. Lectures, remarks and memoranda include the texts of both formal and informal speeches delivered by Hughes at academic and political conferences, special events, and on television programs. The section also includes interviews of Hughes and testimonies by Hughes about academic colleagues. Hughes' writings from his undergraduate and graduate studies and two folders of teaching materials complete the series.
  - Articles and essays
    - Autobiographical, 1961-1979 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - "The Course of the De Gasperi Regime", 1949 January (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - "Italy: Toward a Christian Democratic - Regime'", 1949 November (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - "The Act of Containment: A Balance Sheet", 1950 December (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - "The End of Political Ideology", 1951 Spring (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - "Transatlantic Misunderstanding: Realities and Abstractions", 1951 Autumn (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - "Gaullism: Retrospect and Prospect,", 1951 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - "The Intellectual as Corrupter", 1952 July (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - "Second Thoughts on an Old Relationship", 1952 September (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - "The Early Diplomacy of Italian Fascism: 1922-1932,", 1953 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - "The Crisis of Italian Christian Democracy", 1954 Spring (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - "Review Essay: The Problem of Limited Collaboration", 1954 June (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Thirty-five Years After Versailles, 1954 August (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - "Gaetano Mosca and the Political Lessons of History,", 1954 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - "Reinterpretation of the Aftermath of the Risorgimento in Four Successive Interpretations", 1955 October (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - "Western Strategy and Economic Revolution", 1956 February (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - California-The America to Come, 1956 May (Box 12, Folder 17)